Okay, welcome back to this BST and No Recursive Function session that we started in the last
video.
So if you recall in the last video we talked about how to insert elements in a BST, no
one at a time, right?
If you remember these were the elements that we inserted in the BST in this order and
we noted that if you start with 10, the 10 becomes your root of the BST and then following
the sequence we kept on inserting one element at a time while preserving all the BST property
right and there were two sensual property that we wanted to ensure one was structural
property that at no time your tree should have more than any node in your tree should
have more than two elements or two two childrens and then the other property which was concerning
the values that you can put at a parent or child was that you know every child or you
know everything that comes in the right you know subtree of a parent should be greater
than the parent value and everything that comes on the left subtree should be less than
on this.
So this was the property that you mentioned in the very beginning.
This is a standard BST property that should be true for any BST, okay?
So if you are claiming that you are trying to maintain a BST while this insert or delete
operation happens on your rata structure then you have to somehow make sure or give proof
of correctness why this is maintained through every insert or not releasing and that's
what we try to do at least for the insertion in the last video right.
So all nodes in the left subtree should have values less than the nodes value was the first
property and in all node in its right subtree have the value no greater than the nodes value
both left and right subtree must also satisfy the BST property, okay?
So it's not that I mean this property should be only true for the topmost or let's say root
node.
I mean all the nodes should have this property and that's how you know I mean and if this
is true for every node in your tree then you can call it a BST, okay?
And we saw some examples then we started you know creating a BST from scratch in the
last video where we try to create you know BST when the elements were coming in this order
where you first saw 10, 10, 50, 37, 10, 20, 20, and 40, we justified and first we looked
at the overall workflow that we would most probably want to implement later on in Python
but then the important point was that throughout this no workflow or adding or inserting different
elements in this existing BST we try to maintain the BST property right?
That's why I said that now whenever you add a node you immediately add no two children
to it so that you remember that you cannot have no more than two children and none represents
that there is nothing you know present at the present moment in the tree at this particular
position and you follow whatever was the property and then you can find a logical way to insert
it either in the left subtree or right subtree or the root node, okay?
And you keep going down until you find the suitable place to insert it and then this was
our discussion so you know so at the end of all this insertion where we wanted to insert
all these elements into a BST what we get is something like this right? So this was our
final tree that came as an output after having all those inserts and in the sequence that
were not given to us. So let's say I mean somehow if you have you know if you implement the BST
insert method and want to do it not by hand but want to call program to insert let's say these
elements one after another so at the end what should you expect you should expect a tree like
this right? And I also hinted in the very beginning that no we can represent these trees using
dictionary right? So the final dictionary that you know represent this tree should look something
like this I mean so I want to go through this code slowly to see whether it makes sense or not.
Does this dictionary represent the same tree that we formed here? Okay so let me help you with
some of the nodes and then I'll leave the other for you to explore in your free time so what
was the root tree so let's say I mean this tree is a dictionary so this is how we represent a
dictionary you know if you recall I mean we identify dictionary with some name let's say call here
this dictionary to be tree because you know our intention is to somehow represent this whole tree
using our dictionary so we give it a name as tree and then we start the curly braces and
in curly braces here okay and in our tree essentially what you are trying to you know store I mean
at the end what should be there I mean your left subtree is none right and then your right subtree
is a big tree right you know which which if you want you know a tree to be represented as
dictionary then the right subtree itself is a dictionary so this is how you should interpret it
and the value at the root node is 10 so this is what this tree you know dictionary is trying to
no capture the value is 10 so this value represents the value of the node and then since you know
this this is the root node you know this tree actually represents the root node of this whole tree
so for every you know root node you have you know three things right we said or I mean for any
node you have three you know information that you want to store so what is the value present there
what is the left subtree that is present there and what is the right subtree that is present there
so that's why this tree feels you know these three keys are there in this dictionary and the
values corresponding to these three keys will be what I discussed right the first one represents
the value or key represents what's the actual value you know kept at that node the left key
represents what is the left subtree and the right key represents what is the right subtree and you
could see on the you know for left we have kept none right because no we wanted to capture this
particularly so here you can see left is not so now we keep keep it here is not but what about
can you see a curly brace no starting here right you can see a curly brace starts here
and from this point onward to this point you know inside there is no curly braces what
we do is we represent another tree because remember when we are talking about this may you know
main you know root node here which is 10 it's right style is not you know one node right it's a
complete you know BST itself right it's another you know smaller BST so if if you represent this
BST using dictionary then no at the right no of key no corresponding to the right key the value
that you will have will actually be a dictionary right and I mean you can just follow this recursive
nature of this dictionary and then guess know what what should be the let's say root node of the
right subtree this is the right subtree right which appears at the right hand side of
or not as a right child of the node 10 and 10 was a you know root node for our main let's say
tree the bigger tree but for this you know right as a right child you again have a dictionary
or a tree BST which we want to represent with DST you know BST so what is the root node of this
no BST what is the value kept at this root node so this is what is what how you know we represent it
the value kept is 50 and again this no right subtree will have no value as well as left subtree
and right subtree of this you know current right subtree that we are looking at okay so again
I mean left hand side is a tree BST is expected to be a BST and right hand side is also expected
to be a BST so that's why you know we kept here you can see I mean for this no smaller right subtree
which start from here and goes up to no this place okay so we have left key which no
represents a complete tree right which which which is encoded up to this point and also a right key
corresponding to which you again have a dictionary which represents the right subtree of this one
okay and you know I'll leave you for you to look at it a little carefully and you know
convince yourself that this is indeed what this no figure represents okay and this is important
because you know say because you know when you will be writing Python program to insert elements
I mean we will be following no this kind of representation for a BST okay so we want to
represent this BST using a binary such a there so this you know binary such is using dictionary
and if you use dictionary and this is the you know most natural way to encode this information
okay now knowing that our current tree is always you know always looks like this I want to now
know right a function which will help me insert a new element let's say you know in existing tree
so before than that I mean before going to the madat mean function I've already written here
you know helper function for you to just see what is the status of the tree right now okay because
here it was difficult right to see this you know clumsy you know code block corresponding to a
dictionary and figure out what was the left and right thing the ideal situation of scenario might
be some displaying this dictionary in this you know form but then I mean this is also not that
easy because of the nature of tree how it grows right you know you have to represent it in
the window that is available to you so what we instead do is you know we try to represent the
same tree using this kind of no notation where the root is 10 and the left I mean this again the
same so you go through this you know function offline and try to see how it when and given
given any root node for a dictionary can print the dictionary for you okay so this is an alternate
way to you know print the same no tree which is which looks like this okay so I'm not going to
discuss this function right now I leave it for you to no figure out how this function can take any
tree of not this kind which is given as dictionary and you print something like this
here where you can see no root node is 10 the left child is none right child is itself of you
know bigger tree again you know from this point onward to this point and then right child of this
is again a tree like this okay so this is certainly now simpler to you know visualize
then this other than you know this particular code which is a complete description of the
BST in using dictionary so we'll be using you know calling this function and again and again when we
let's insert something you know in a dictionary or no we remove something from it is dictionary okay
so now let's come to the actual function which we want to not develop right now so what we
want to do is we want to know so whatever we discuss in the previous video like I mean how to
insert a given element into an existing BST so that after insertion the BST remains the BST
because the new tree that you get is also BST so that whole logic of inserts and we want to now
encode using a Python program is what we are trying to do right now okay so for such a function
I mean can you guess what should be the argument for such such a function I mean BST insert function
so you need to think right at the existing tree BST and the new value that you want to insert
into it okay so these are the you know two information that you know would like to pass to the
okay to this no BST insert so while we are passing root no because root itself is a dictionary right
remember I mean the root node is a dictionary which has all the information about the BST okay
so that's why it's not enough to just pass the root node because root node itself you know is a
dictionary and that dictionary has information about all other element right left child right child
and all the following left and right child of those no trees subject so it's good to pass root
and the value that you want to insert to this you know BST insert function
now let's try to you know develop this function so once let's say if we have this this information
with us if it is you know given to us the root node and the value so the very thing and the first
thing that we do is we we check the you know base guess kind of thing right I mean let's say what if
your root itself is none okay that that may be true right because in the very beginning when you
start no building that no BST there may not be any element at all okay and a good way to
no represent that would be that you know you assign this root value which is not
okay so so that may be so the base guess I mean and you need to know how to handle this
base guess right because even when you are you know inserting elements you remember I mean we
were going down either left subtree or right subtree and the moment you want to this you know
take this call whether I sell insert at this position or not was
somehow decided based on whether none is present there or not okay so if none is present then only
you can you know insert you know something so that's why I mean the very so the base case is what
we we need to solve first so let me so what we are trying to do is now define the base case
so I mean this will be a row if you remember see this this whole function structure would be
recursive in nature because not any moment in time when you are comparing it with the root node
or the root node of the subtree that you are currently looking at you want to say whether it's
the element should go to the right subtree or the left subtree right so you may want to again call
the same function with a different argument I mean your value will be same but you know a root
will change right and you will keep doing it until you hit the base no no case and the best
case is when you see that your root which is right now your point where pointing to is actually
not right remember I mean so this is what happened right in the previous cases when we were discussing
this one by one the moment I decided that no 30 you know goes to the right of 50 so to the
no 30 is goes to the right of 10 and then we compare it with 50 and then we decided to go
towards this no left subtree and we immediately encountered this non-value so it indicated that now
now we cannot go any no further so the no the root for the left subtree was none right and
root for the left subtree was none that's why you know we decided that no we have reached the
correct position but now we cannot go down further so if we see that the root of our
no going to root of our current dictionary is none and we are we have been asked to put it
in this you know the subtree better replace this none with the value that I came up
having in my hand for example in this case no 30 was in my hand right and I inserted 30 here
and I created left and right child immediately for this 30 okay so this is the action that you need
to you know take when you have reached the correct position okay but I mean you have to somehow
say this explicitly in your code okay and if you have reached that place and how do you know that
you have reached that place by checking whether the root has become none or not so can we you know
write down the same logic here maybe where we are writing can we you know write down this
base case thing so that this is no kind of base case where we know that we have reached the
place where we want to put the value that is provided to us okay now if so what is that
base case now if root is none because we are representing with none this this none in a way
is representing in our case that no there is nothing you know down in the line if you go want to go
ahead okay so in this case what we want to do is we want to return our dictionary okay so what's
the dictionary that you want to return now you want to put there this value right so what you want to
in the value field I will you know pass whatever value no comes as an argument to me
and then I will immediately create you know left and so if you know that your root the root that
currently you know is in your hand is none then at that moment itself you have decided that okay
I want to know maybe know make a small tree and then return this thing right so the return
so you you are returning a small tree where your value is this one and you have to left thing
in left we none because you know right now I know that there is nothing you know down say this is
the last element that I'm not trying to insert so I should make it in form of a node and this is
how I represent a node which does not have any you know child so for that node you have to tell
what is the value what is the left child and what is the right child the left child is in none and
the right child is also okay so this should also be none right so no this way we created a dictionary
and remember I mean this is a dictionary right because I kept it in curly paste so this
represents my you know current node that I have inserted and I will just return it okay so this
you know function actually you know returns to the updated tree okay but this remember the
base case when you know that the root itself is none but it might not be correct right because
you know in in so it may be correct only maybe in the very first go when you are starting with the
empty let's say BST but in most of the other case when you start your insertion process you
already have a not tree and you want to figure out what is the correct position where I shall go
and then try to insert it right so most of the other insertors will not you know immediately hit
this no base case okay so we will start exploring from the root and you you want to navigate to
that place where you want to keep this okay so this is what we call you know recursive step so
so let me call it you know one the base case let's just call it one is the base case and then
the recursive cases the most no general case where so let me you know call it
recursive step and in the recursive step what we do is no you have a value and you have a root
and if you root is not none so if root is none you know that no this is this statement is executed
and you immediately written right this is what the meaning of the semantics of this written
that you don't execute anything below but if root is not none then you get to this recursive step
which says that now now now what we need to do we need to compare right whether the value is left
in the root value or the non greater than root value and depending upon what is the you know
current scenario I would do different set of actions okay so let me in or write it down so let me
say if our value in hand is less than the value that is present at root and how to access that
value do you remember this was the syntax that we use for accessing a key value for a dictionary
right so we want to compare the value that is at my hand with the value that is no present
at the root okay and the way to access that value is this root followed by this is square
bar bracket and this name of the key where you store those value and the key name was value
so we want to make this check in the positive case when let's say this value is less than
root value what do we want to do I mean we want to know go to the left subtree and then search with
the correct position of this value and insert there right so what so now in a simple way not
declarative way if you want to say what you want to do you can say that now go to this left subtree
and insert this in the left subtree okay so this is very easy to you know understand that if my
value is less than the root value I know that the place for this current value is in the left
subtree so can I again I mean say that just go to the you know or maybe you know call this BST
insert function again on this new root which is the left child of my you know current root
and try to figure out where to insert it so instead of giving the complete logic again what I can
actually in a very succinct way say that why not call this function again on the on a different
input right because right now I can say that you go to the you know left root on the left subtree
and then insert this value and that's done and you repeat this process keep repeating this
process until you hit this none value because no what you have to do for none is already included
here in the logic okay since you you have already said what to do if you encounter none here
maybe here you can be a little bit more lazy and then describe your whole process by just saying
that okay I want to repeat the same set of action maybe I by calling the same function again at this
not with this new you know parameters or argument so need to be more precise let me write down
what I want to say so here what we are trying to do is we're trying to say that no you call so
so I know I know two thing that no my left subtree has to be updated right because no this new
element is less than the root element so it will somewhere go into the left subtree and left
subtree has to be updated in some you know all modified in some way so that this new element
can be accommodated in the left subtree is what we want to do so the way to say that is my
root so my you know current roots left subtree is how so no this index
helps us access the left subtree okay so what is the left of the root is what we are trying to
update okay so we are trying to update it and how do we want to update it we are saying that now
I want to call this BST insert
with the new argument okay so what I want to say is no you pass now to BST insert the left
subtree which is no access to using this and then this value okay and the justification
what is the justification for calling this function because I know that my value should go to
the left subtree so what I'm saying is you insert this value into the left subtree and how to get
the left subtree of the currently by you know using this syntax so this syntax remember this is
not different than this one right originally this function was called on root but now since I know
that it is less than the root I am calling again the same function on the left subtree of the
no this you know main tree and this is the way to you know call the same function BST insert
and remember I mean this is why we call it you know recursive function because you know inside
the definition of BST insert we are again calling BST insert but in this call the argument
is not same okay now we are calling the same BST insert with a different argument and this
difference in argument actually reflects the difference know in the tree that where we want to
now store this value okay and once you know call this function on this you know different tree
which is a subtree left subtree of the main tree with the same value the return of return type
of this function will itself be a tree okay so and what will be the tree the updated tree okay so
what is the tree after insertion so now you will get the updated left subtree you know as an
output as a return from here and that you want to assign to the current roots left side right
because this is what we you know want to do right saying that now go to the left subtree and insert
this value is same as you know as saying that you update I explicitly pass you the left subtree
and the value and you return me a new you know tree with this value kept there and then
assign this to my current left subtree so this is no another way of saying the same thing okay so
if you don't do this assignment you know then nothing happens right because this function is
called it returns something which you are not trying to use to update your current tree because
your current tree is this you know represented by this root and you want to update the left subtree
of your current subtree now after insertion you know this insertion happens and since this returns
the updated tree I want to insert that into the left and side okay so now please I mean this may
be a little troublesome troublesome to many of you due to the recursive nature of thinking but
it's not that difficult if you spend some time I hope you will be able to make sense of what I said
just now okay so this is the recursive call and so what the function here is doing is calling
itself okay so let me write it down the function calls itself
with the
with the left child as
did you know right
or the new root better say
okay so when I decided that this element should go to my you know left subtree I again
ask you know call the same function with a different argument and the argument is now the
left side of the current no root that I was in okay so it will go and do you know it's job
but if this is not the case let's say you know if this is not the case so what what should
write for the L's case
okay you guess the L's case so what will the L's case I mean assuming that there are no two
elements are let's say equal so they're all distinct so if value is not less than the root value
the value should be greater than the root value right and in that case what would you like to do
you'd like to do just the opposite of what you did just now right we would like to update our
right subtree right by inserting this new element into my right subtree and how to do that so can we
copy the same you know syntax here and then maybe
we paste it here and what what are the changes that you need to do here instead of
saying that I want to update my left subtree I want to say that now I want to update my
right subtree and what shall I put there so the new value inserted in the
right subtree of my current thing this is what no I want again so what does it function does
here the function calls itself with the right child as new you know
so what are we doing here
the function call itself with the
the right child as the new row okay so so this is what the function is intended to do and so
depending upon what is the situation it will either call the same function on the left subtree or
the right subtree okay and since this is recursive in nature I mean if you don't you know find
there again the none case I mean you call this function again and again until you hit this
because no when when this function is again called remember with a different route and value
what will happen so the function definition says that the next call again checks this in the very
beginning this is the very first step of the next call also okay so so remember I mean we have
written this function only one time so this in the logic of execution but this is not the
this whole definition of function is not the execution of the function when you call this
function with some argument the whole you know this program sequence will be executed one after
another another and if you know a function it is calling again itself inside you know it's
outer call then the current call actually gets suspended and no the number so the implementation
or the compiler implements this kind of calls in such a way so that it stores all the information
about the current call and then you know put it in some form of a track data structure and tries to
call again the same function on some smaller input and try to execute that function so again I
mean if this happens to call itself no due to the kind of data it has so the second call also
will be put on hold and then the third call will start executing so that's why I mean this may be
a little non you know intuitive or I mean a little difficult or tricky for you but if you think
closely I mean just write down these things and try to execute this code on a given tree structure
you will be able to figure out I mean how the control flows when you actually run this kind of
program okay so I will come again to this but let me first you know finish the logic of this
program so this is the right thing and then at the end what you do is so remember I need to return
something right because in these cases we have not returned anything right so since you updated
the route you have to return this route okay we need to return this updated route otherwise
this program is not complete right because in the base case you return something explicitly
okay and you have to always return the updated subtree right so what if it is not the base case
I mean you have updated certainly the route but you if you don't return it I mean it is not
available to the outer function okay so that's why it's very much important to you know return it
explicitly here okay and I mean there can be alternative way of implementation but in our way
of implementation what we are saying is we are always explicitly returning you know the updated
tree and then using that updated tree to update my current you know route trick so this is what
no we are doing so that's why I mean I'm explicitly returning this route and I will use it to
maybe you know update me horizontally okay so good so now since we have this thing there are
a couple of things that I already noted one was the base case right this none kind of situation
where recursion because since this function is recursive in nature you know it needs some
stopping point right I mean when will this kind of recursive logic stop so this base case is always
you have to clearly identify what is the base case when you identify that now there will be no
further call to the same function and you want to stop and you know maybe put the value there
and return this thing okay so this is what we called you know the base case recursion requires
a stopping point so in a BST we stop when we reach this none okay this is the only line where a
new dictionary is actually created so every other call simply you know moves through existing
you know dictionary and then tries to come at the right position okay so another thing that I
pointed was this you know persistent thing that the state persists so the and the compiler which
tries to you know implement this kind of logic always maintains a call stack you know something
called call stack again we will not go into the detail of what how exactly this is but
in a broad sense I mean when I mean for example in this case when BST insert calls itself
the current function execution is suspended or when it calls the function again okay and it stays
in the memory I mean it's not that you suspend it and you forget about everything because you need
to remember this information when you come back from the call okay when the call let's say the
execution of you know this call this particular call now ends okay so this is again recursive
called to the same function so when execution of this so this is you know calling a function right
inside itself so when execution of this ends you want to again return back to the main function
that called this thing to do some remaining job right because there are some something remaining
right you want to assign the value that is written from this you know next this you know call to
the same function recursive call to the same function and assign that into the root and then
return it so you you don't want to lose you know these steps so that's why you want to come back
to this so this control flow is you know managed by compiler and this is how it happens and that
temporarily it will suspend the execution of this thing because remember it cannot execute you know
this line until it has you know completely evaluated this expression right and assign that
expression into this thing so it needs to suspend because you know evaluating this expression is
not possible without you know calling the same function again so that's why I mean it's suspending
so if you understand the semantics of assignment operation properly then it should not be that
difficult right because the you know the semantics of assignment operation says that you have to
first evaluate the right hand side expression and then only you can assign it to the left hand
side okay so anything that comes after this assignment cannot actually happen if the right hand
side expression is not evaluated so it has to be suspended right I mean until everything but then
when you go to evaluate this right hand side is a new function call although on the same function
but it's a new call to the same function so it will start again you know call it will pass a value
and the whole execution of this you know body of the function definition will start with a new
argument okay and until that execution ends you don't get this exact value for this expression
and if you don't get exact value for this expression you cannot continue execution of this
so this is a kind of a you know temporary preemption of the current call calling it on the small
on calling the same function on a smaller input and waiting till the function call returns me
some value and then proceeding with my current call okay so this way I mean you go you may go
quite a lot I mean deep down this kind of a function call and then when you returning you are
actually trying to you know finish whatever was the remaining in your caller function okay so there
are one one there is a caller function and there is a you know call function right so the one who calls
this same function again is called caller and then the one is which is being called is you know
call call function so this logic is very important to understand and it should not be difficult if you
understand the semantics of assignment okay so just try to work so it in that logical sense
that we discussed earlier and you will be able to make no sense so the suspension is what I would
okay so let me maybe use a diagram that I have here to describe the same thing you know this
state persistent thing or you know this call stack thing so I have written some description of
this so you can just read this and offline to understand what we discuss now but a good visual
representation of the same thing is presented here okay so what we are saying here is that
that if you want to insert 40 right into the into a BST which is already know like this
now you have done all these insertions already so your BST will be some will look something like
this right and if you want to insert 40 to this BST so what you will do you will call this
function right which is let me first you know compile this code you know before we
do any further execution now let me finish it so this is already complete so
this function is already and let me also compile this piece of code which is responsible for
printing the tree and this is working properly now we come to this description of the same
no function calls okay so when function calls when a recursive function call happens what happens
and can we look and understand it visually so this is what is being explained here so inserting
40 into our BST which already has know this kind of a structure what how this control flows
is what I am going to discuss now in the step one what you do is you call this function insert
function with no 40 and the root node 10 right because no currently our root node is 10 so if
you call it with you know 10 what happens so inside this function call it compares and it finds
that 40 is greater than 10 so it says that now go to the right right so going to write means
again calling with this same same function insert function with 40 but with a modified node right
I think you know the the order of node is just the opposite of what no we have written here right
I mean so so first you pass the no root node and then the value but I mean never mind I mean you
you can you know keep in mind that this is the first okay so we need to pass this to information
node and 40 so assume here I mean the 40 is the value and the node position is no 10 so when you
call with which this insert function with no 10 then and you know value 40 so it goes and checks
the condition and the again calls the same BST insert function with the value same value 40 but now
at a different node right because no 40 was greater than 10 so it now calls the same you know
BST insert function on this smaller substrate and while calling this function you have to always
pass the root node and the value that you want to okay so when this call happens this you know
subcall to the right subtree happens so what happens the main call in which you have again
call this same function so the main call I mean this call which our step one gets suspended okay so
it is paused now why it's paused because it's you know waiting for this particular call to in
and return value and then only this call can go ahead right because this is this was the
as a no semantic surface assignment now what happens so this is you know pause right so your
execution of the first call to this insert is actually paused at this point and then you again
call the same function with different argument and this call again starts executing remember
this is this is paused this isn't this is halted at the moment when this is executing so when this
is executing again you check 40 you know with respect to the 50 and you figure out that now what
you should go to the left subtree so if it has to go to the left subtree you again call the same
function with a different node value why because the left subtree is root was 30 so you call it with
this root node 30 so I mean this is not the correct way to call I mean this is not syntactically
current but I'm trying to just explain you the logic I mean you can replace this syntax with the
exact functions in text that we have written above and everything will work fine like like instead
of you know instead we have BST insert and we have just the opposite order of passing things and
no you cannot pass value I mean you have to pass the exact dictionary right so but I mean keeping
all those things aside let's try to you know follow the main logic of the function call and
no it's suspension till the inner call gets completed now remember now when you when again
this insert you know obviously insert is called on a new node with the same value this execution
is also halted okay so the second execution which is started for the function call is also halted
and a third execution or function call starts again and that function call is you know again
insert the same value at the different node position at right I mean for a different you know
subtree which is no represented here okay so again I mean it goes and checks so when you call it
with this you know this logic is executed and it figures out now you have to go right okay so now
you have to go right and you know when you see what is at the right of 30 I mean I have not
represented here but it there is a none here right so right of 30 is a none so you want again
want to call this function with a none so when you call this function again with none remember
this execution also is halted right so this third you know call to the function is also halted
and it again calls into goes into the fourth steps and calls the same function again on a new input
but this time the new input is you know new node is none okay and you know this is a interesting
point right I mean because we have already taken care of this logic inside our code in the very
you know beginning which is the base case you remember the base case let me you know bring
you the code the base case what we check was if our root becomes none then at that moment I
am not calling any other you know function right I am simply returning the value okay so this chain
of calls that we we have seen just now when we started with the root node it went down deep down
no until this point but at this point so it hits the base case and the base case is this none case
and it's none none we're seeing that node is now none it can actually create a small you know
dictionary and return to you so after this return happens what where do you go I mean your control
flows back to this call it because this was suspended this was the last suspended function call
okay so you will go back to this last suspended function call back to step three and since you
are waiting for this insert which happened now you can complete your execution of that no particular
function no call and update update accordingly okay and when you're you know this function call
again you know completes you go back to this you know function call and you resume from where you
pause you complete the logic and then similarly you go back to 40 okay so this is how it happens
right so back to step three you go now where you know called with this you know 30 remember
the step three you called with this 30 right and you you suspended this function because no
sorry you suspended that function you know temporarily because you wanted this result to be
available right before you can proceed so now since you have those values and now you can
proceed execution of that okay and once the execution is complete for that call again
the previous call which was suspended in step two this call now gets resume you know with because
I mean now it has the value which it wants to use to assign the variable on the left hand side
right so it can use that value and you know that function call again complete and when that is
complete it again returns some value okay which can be used by the very first function call
that was suspended and when that function call gets this value the whole execution actually
okay so this is how actually the recursive you know function call no we get simply maintained okay
so function starts calling itself and the caller function gets suspended the moment it
start calling you know it calls the call function but the call function again I mean start executing
and depending upon the logic and the data kind of input it took it may again either return a value
or it may call another same function again one more time so in your stack you will have now two
function waiting for again the next execution to finish and then return value but
termination of this kind of chain has to be guaranteed by the programmer right because if you
don't take care of this base case then you see I mean there is a you know infinite recursion that
may keep going down where will you stop okay so it is very important to identify what will be my
stopping logic and that is what we encode here is a base case okay so we encode the stopping logic
in the base case and then you know try to encode other logics no when to call the same function on
the left subtree or right subtree is what we have encoded in the code okay so just so with this I
mean we now know how this whole control flow works when you call a recursive function and again
this is the same thing in a big tutorial form I mean and you can go through it again offline okay
so please go through it you know but it is slowly to understand exactly how the control
for this kind of recursive call okay now okay now just to you know show you that you know things
that problem working properly so since we have already created a BST insert function now can we
use that BST insert function to do actual insert right so for that what we say is we create
empty tree initially which is done let's say I mean I have a very empty tree which is
represented by a my tree and I want to insert certain element into this my tree okay so what I can
do is I can just call my you know BST insert no one by one for each of these elements right because
these elements have to be inserted in this order which first 10 then 50 30 70 20 and then 40
so what the syntax here is doing is that I am calling the same function which is no this BST insert
function okay by passing my tree and the values in the order which is given here because see
this is the syntax no for well in insertion sequence and this is the insertion is released
it will pick one by one all these elements and then call this BST insert
with the existing tree which is initially you know none
with these values and whatever it you know returns
I use it to update my current tree okay and this is how it should work right because if you
don't assign it to my tree then every time my tree is you know none so you have to we want to
assign it to my tree so my tree gets updated after every instruction and we want to repeat this
thing until this whole all of these elements are inserted so this logic should be you know
clear to you it's not a very difficult logic and then what we are doing is that we are also
displaying our partially constructed tree from inside this for loop and after every insertion how
the tree looks like okay and if you run this let us see what happens so when we run this you can
see this is how it is building so I mean this kind of a visual proof of the correctness of our
function that when you are inserting 10 so this is what you know we wanted to pre right when we are
inserting 10 so this is what happens initially you had none right because we start with none so
so your root becomes now none and you left child and right child both are none so
so instead of none we write n here capital N here but it means none both the left hand right
right hand child said none so when you insert 50 in the second iteration okay you already had
you know this tree right and then the 50 goes to the right child remember 10 was the root left
notice none right node was none which is now updated to the 50 followed by this right because
you know 50 also has to child right by default we always know just to maintain this structural
you know invariant what we say whenever you create a new node you just create you know to child
for that node and just keep you know assign them value now so now this is what should happen right when
your second iteration goes and this is what's happening right because it's being printed from you
know inside this code block when you insert 30 this is what happens right 30 goes into the left
child of 50 remember this was the root node for 50 and the left child now becomes no 30 and again
I mean in a similar way for 30 you're left and right and none because and this is what we follow
to maintain the structural invariant and the right child should be none right you're not changing
the right child of 50 okay so the whole logic is you know working properly and you can just go
through slowly one by one to see whether you know you get exactly the kind of clear that you
expected in the beginning okay so you know this is this is all about basically that I wanted to
discuss today but remember that you know in any data structure you not only insert you also
may want to you know delete something from the data structure and you may also want to
search whether a particular element is you know presented the data structure or not and
you know the purpose of search may be different in different cases I mean in some cases you may
just for example in the case of BST we may want to just search whether a value appears in my
BST or not and if the value appears somewhere just return me the the subtree where this value appears
as the root value okay so this may be no one of the search requirement on our BST and I
would request you to take it as a homework and implement this search function okay so you can
think again I mean in a similar way the implemented insert function and try to come up with maybe
a BST search function no which is recursive in nature you may also try to no think can you
implement this kind of you know search on BST without using regression okay so take this as
homework for you so let me you know I have already written it for you so can you implement you know
if you follow the how BST works okay now based on that understanding of BST can you write down
a BST search function the one version I requested you to write as a recursive function where
if you have been given a BST by providing root of the BST and a target value that you want to
search in the BST it should return the you know the root where or the node where this value exists
if it exists if it doesn't exist then you can in that case no return none so this is a function
signature that I have no provided you and can you do the same exercise by writing not as a recursive
function but as a maybe iterative function I mean you can use even loops to do this okay so think
about this problem and try to solve this properly I mean these two examples at least try to
complete the implementation for these two functions signature is what I'm asking you to okay so
so with this I would like to conclude not today's lecture so please spend some time working
through this example and especially solving this assignment problem and I will meet you in the next
video. Thank you.